FORUM ARVIND CHAUHAN

New Jersey, USA | forumchauhan06@gmail.com

Passionate architect with a focus on sustainability, renewable energy and reduced ecological footprint with 8 Years of Academic background. Bachelors in architecture from Vadodara, India and Master's in urban and Regional Planning from New York, USA. Experience with low-cost, energy efficient homes, wooden-frame construction, and sustainable housing typologies.

EDUCATION

New York Institute of Technology, New York

Master of Science in Architecture and Urban Design Sep 2022 - May 2023

Navrachana University, India

Bachelor of Architecture Aug 2017 - May 2022

ITM UNIVERSE - School of Art, Architecture and Design, India

Diploma in Architecture Aug 2014 - May 2017

EXPERIENCE

Design Studio, India

Intern Architect May 2017 - Aug 2017

- Engaged in designing layouts of commercial and residential projects.
- Generating presentation drawings for client meetings and presentations of schemes.
- Site visits and communicating with clients.

Local X Society (LXS), India

Intern Architect Jan 2021 - June 2021

- Assisted in Designing Residential projects and commercial projects.
- Worked as a part of Historic Restoration and Preservation.
- Studied about restoration Materials and their uses in real time.
- Participated in International Competitions and Conducted Workshops
- Worked for the Old House Redevelopment and Public Realms in the surroundings.

Dwip Associates, India

Junior Architect June 2022 - Aug 2022

- Analysed the plans and conducted monthly site visits.
- Understood the functioning and process underlying the development of a housing scheme. concentrating on the scale and quality of spaces.
- Involved in generating floor patterns with optimal use of material and space.
- Understanding the layout of large-scale projects and their divisions.

Freelancing Projects, India

May 2017 - Aug 2022

- Worked for multiple projects at small scale including a few interior designs and some aesthetic elements like a piece of furniture.
- More focused on exploring new materials and engaging with client's need and addressing them with the budget constraints.
- Involved with a group of designers for the final design outcome.

Participations

Regional and International

May 2015 - Aug 2023

- Certified course in 'Urban Condensers Workshop 'at Polytechnic University of Madrid, Spain (2019)
- Studied and learnt the principles of urban interventions at a city's micro graphic level.
- Collaborated and had understandings about neighbourhood and the context.
- Certified course in 'Living Walls in Urban landscaping' at University of Chile, Chile (2023)
- Learnt about the insertions of Living walls and its types on how to conduct sustainable building facades in interior and exterior.
- Interacted with the participants and had a larger prospect of their ideas.
- Got recognition for Actively curating different design related workshops in Undergraduate University.
- Entry level Inter University competitions at Undergraduate University.
- *Various workshops* including Model making, Wood cutting, Furniture, Brick moulding and Cement moulding.
- Volunteered and established a Non- Profitable Organization that focused on needs of the community and served them food and education.
- Various Design Competitions during Undergraduate programme.
- Curated the Design x Design for LXS in Delhi which interacted with many renowned architects and their works.
- Writing Skills Published in an arthrology for national selling book.
- Mapping of old city in Vadodara, India for the Heritage and Preservation Organization.
- Learnt about the Act of mapping and how the thresholds are important for the future reclamation of land their usages.
- More focused on how to redeem the property and make it more worthy making it a symbol of Heritage Importance for the region.

TECHNOLOGY AND SKILLS

Technology: Autodesk AutoCAD, Rhinoceros, Grasshopper, Revit, Sketchup, Microsoft Office, Adobe photoshop, Adobe InDesign, Adobe Lightroom, Adobe Premier, Qgis

Skills: Communication, Teamwork, Time Management, Strong project management and collaboration skills, Great presentation and communication skills, Extensive knowledge of sustainable design, building codes and other regulations, Great computing skills